hello everyone welcome to my channel i'm
the dividend portfolio
and today we're going to be talking
about prudential as a potential dividend
stock
investment to get started here we're
going to go through the core business of
the company
we're going to look at their financial
history and financial growth
opportunities
their current valuation their dividend
and i'm gonna give some final thoughts
and
of course the disclaimers
so just get started with um prudential
is a very diversified company
they operate throughout the entire globe
in
basically three different areas so the
first area involves a global investment
management or
pgim segment and pgi segment has
many different services they provide
services for fixed
income for private capital
real estate finances real estate
different types of investments and
global partners
many of the revenues generated for the
company in the
pgim segment come through asset
management fees
and transaction fees and also fees
associated with sales of the
assets that they're managing another
large
percent of the business is the united
states business
and so the united states business is
broken up into many different
divisions they have the u.s workplace
solutions division
which offers a variety of products
including iras
record-keeping administrative services
and general separate account
valuations furthermore they also have
products like the group life insurance
and the group disability insurance
along with individual annuities and
a variety of other individual life
services
the international business is the
last major segment of prudential and
they offer a number of very similar
products including life insurance
protection
retirement products annuity products
and accidental and health products
so essentially the the company is is
kind of broken up into these
three different major divisions and
interestingly enough when you look at
their investment report what you can see
here is that
these business these business segments
are rather well diversified
the united states business and the
international business
have a very similar in percent of
the total earning contributions as of q3
so 42
for international business versus 41 for
the us business
and then pgm comes at you know about
half that with about 17
so they do have a diversified set of
different businesses that operate
throughout the entire globe
looking at specifically their financial
history over the last decade what we can
see
is with the exception of the despite
that i'm generally from the end of 2010
to begin 2011 all the way through 2019
the companies had this relatively steady
growth in
revenue operating income and
net income with actually a moderate
decrease
in long-term debt over the last five
years
looking forward prudential is also
expected to have some growth going
forward
so here we're looking at is the analyst
estimated annual eps growth
through 2022 for prudential
and also for some other companies in the
life and health insurance industry
so specifically we here we have manulife
financial corporation
mfc and also aflac incorporated afl
and essentially we can see in this graph
here is that prudential is
expected by analysts to have the the
strongest eps growth over the next two
years
out of these three companies and a large
part of that growth will be driven from
their plans to actually expand their
operation throughout the entire globe
now prudential's international
businesses continue to develop in japan
where they currently have over 30
billion dollars
in assets they're managing but
they're also seeking to expand in other
economies with rising middle classes and
now this includes
places like china latin america africa
and southeast
asia furthermore the united states
business
is currently developing end-to-end
engagement models to help meet
consumer demand so we can kind of see
here from the analysts and
from the management prudential is that
the company does have some plans to
really promote some growth going forward
but let's actually take a look at the
valuation of the company so
this company has an appealing um value
to to actually invest in
and we'll start here with the the
forward p ratio
so we can see here is that all three of
these these
different um insurance companies
currently have
very low forward pes and they're all
currently
well below their 10 year p e ratio so we
can see here that prudential's
somewhere around that the eight and a p
e ratio right now
and they're typically just a little shy
of 12.
and um also looking at the the price to
free cash flow ratio
we can see the prudential is is doing
really strong
there so they are about one and a half
right now
compared to their 10-year average of
well over two
and i should say that a and a half is
still
very very good even even not even
considering this this average here
interestingly aflac currently has a
forward price to the free cash flow
actually significantly higher than its
its 10-year medium
and manual life has
a price recast flow right between
prudential and and nav1
also looking at other valuation metrics
looking at the forward adjusted peg we
can see once again the prudential comes
in very strong
having a peg ratio of almost one here
manual life is very similar here and
both these companies are are
significantly less than afflux
at about two not slightly over
another important metric to look at is
price to book ratio now this ratio is
very important
for financial companies
and we can see here that prudential has
a great price to book ratio of
nearly 0.5 on a gap basis which is
significantly below their
five-year average furthermore this
this press-book ratio is is also is also
quite good compared to
these other two insurance companies
at the dividend we can see the
prudential actually does quite well
prudential starting dividend yield is a
whopping 5.6 percent
which is higher than their competitors
and is also
significantly higher than the 10-year
median dividend yield for the company
over the last five years the company has
been growing in at 13
on a compounded adjusted growth rate
basis
which is nearly double what the
competitors have been growing in
in fact even going forward the company
is expected to grow their dividend at
about 6.7 percent over the next few
years
according to seeking alpha which is
still great growth with
their current starting yield they have a
dividend growth rate of about 12 years
and this is
probably where my biggest criticism
would come in with a dividend they did
cut it during the 2008 2009
financial crisis i think it was very
understandable given the situations
going on there
and the situation the company was in and
i think also the regulations put in
place by the government
as well as prudential's reduction of
debt to equity
should help keep this dividend secure
going forward and finally look at the
credit rating we can kind of see this
this
double a minus component here which is a
very great
credit rating from the s p and is really
kind of
speaks to the the security here of the
dividend
also looking at the the payout ratio
here we can see the prudential is
it's still at a reasonable payout ratio
here at about 44
but it is higher than manulife and
aflac's dividend payout ratio
furthermore interest coverage which is
the ability for the company to cover
um their interest which is an important
metric for how much money they have
available to pay the dividend
is is that a solid nearly five for
potential
but this is still lower than the
manulife and aflac
i will also add that there are some
risks associated with the company in the
industry
now for the insurance company industry
they are dependent on
interest rates and as we all know
interest rates are low and they have
been low for quite some time
in fact going forward in united states
and japan
or large regions where prudential
actually does business
their interest rates are expected to
continue to be low
going forward so essentially
this lower interest rate can lead to
essentially lower floats for the company
and can also adversely affect
insurance company premium fortunately
for prudential
they do have a lot of experience dealing
with low interest rates
and have also taken steps to reduce
their dependence on interest rates
and finally their pgim segment
is not really dependent on these
interest rates so diversification also
helps in this scenario
furthermore it's important is for life
insurance companies
is to consider the fact that we are
currently in a global health care crisis
um the effects of this crisis have
actually added to prudential's costs
and um it's important to remember that
over the last nine months the prudential
has actually experienced over 100
million dollars in extra cost due to the
pandemic
but all things considered prudential's
100 million dollars in extra cost due to
the whole global health care crisis
is rather manageable considering how
large the company is
and the fact that they brought in over
60 billion dollars in revenue
over the last trailing 12 months
so kind of taken together here we can
see is is
with credentials that the company is
well positioned to recover from this
this downturn here and they're also
positioned for some growth over the next
few years
the company does come into i think a
very great valuation
specifically their price to book ratios
their free
their price to free cash flow ratios and
also looking at the
the forward price earning ratios and the
price earning growth ratios i think
really highlight how the the valuation
of this company and just
how much it has lagged behind the other
industries
and also behind some of its competitors
the company comes at a very solid
dividend yield of 5.6 percent
and this dividend also looks rather
secure looking at the the company's
financial history
and also on their current coverage of
their dividend and interest
so kind of taken together i think
prudential offers a
solid source of income for dividend
investors so that kind of concludes my
overview of prudential
if you like this please give me a like
or a subscription i would really
appreciate that
also just as some disclaimers i am not a
financial advisor
i am sharing my financial journey for
fun and entertainment purposes only
the different types of grabs and models
used in this analysis
are not guaranteed to be accurate i do
own some of the stocks mentioned today i
recently
started investing in prudential and as
always please consult financial advisor
and do due diligence prior to
investing